The Lives Of The Prophets Part 2
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
Now, things were getting a little bit difficult on Firaun(فرعون).
Because this embarrassing event happened in front of all of the people of Egypt.
So, the evil advisors of Firaun(فرعون) came to him and said;
You need to do something; You can't let things get out of control.
And these are the parasites living under Firaun(فرعون) who are benefiting from the situation; benefiting from the status quo.
Because these oppressive leaders, they don't exist in a vacuum.
Az-Zalamah(اظلمه); the oppressors; these kings; they don't live in a vacuum;
They have an underlying power under them.
They have Chiefs; Al-Mala(اَلمَلاَ); They have advisors; They have a government;
They have people who are serving them and helping them; Otherwise, they can't exist alone.
And Firaun(فرعون); even though he claimed to be God and he claimed to be the owner of Egypt.
لِمُلْكُ مِصَر
Nevertheless, he still had to depend on these people under him.
And these are parasites who are benefiting financially and benefiting from the positions, they are getting under the leadership of Firaun(فرعون).
So, they are looking for their benefit also.
وَقَالَ ٱلْمَلَأُ مِن قَوْمِ فِرْعَوْنَ أَتَذَرُ مُوسَىٰ وَقَوْمَهُۥ لِيُفْسِدُواْ فِى ٱلْأَرْضِ وَيَذَرَكَ وَءَالِهَتَكَ ۚ
The chiefs of Firaun's people said;
Will you leave Musa(موسى) and his people to spread mischief in the land?
And to abandon you and your gods or going to let this happen or going to let this go?
So, they pushed Firaun(فرعون); So he said;
قَالَ سَنُقَتِّلُ أَبْنَآءَهُمْ وَنَسْتَحْىِۦ نِسَآءَهُمْ وَإِنَّا فَوْقَهُمْ قَٰهِرُونَ۝
He said; We will kill their sons and we will let their women live and we have irresistible power over them.
Didn't Firaun(فرعون) issue this order before?
When did he issue it?
When Musa(موسى) was born.
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); When this issue was decreed; Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); What did they say?
أُوذِينَا مِنْ قَبْلِ أَنْ تَأْتِيَنَا
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); they said; We have received harm when you were born and we're receiving harm from you now.
All this trouble is because of you.
They were killing us in the beginning because of you, because of your birth.
That is why our children were killed.
And now our children are killed again; Why?
Because of you another time.
And this is the nature of the people who are not willing to sacrifice anything for the sake of Allah.
People are already humiliated; They're crushed.
And they don't want to move ahead; And they're not willing to give anything.
They want victory;
They want success;
They want position;
But they're not willing to pay the price for it.
And unfortunately, sometimes; we're guilty of doing the same thing.
How come Islam is not established?
How come there is no Khilafah(خِلَافَه)? How come?
And this person, you find him; he's not doing anything and he's blaming the whole Ummah(امة).
And he's the only one who's innocent.
Look at the Muslims! Look at the Muslims! And he's speaking about everyone; but himself.
Why is the problem in Chechnya happening?
Why is the problem in Iraq(عراق) happening?
Why is the problem in Falastine(فلسطين) happening?
Why is it happening in Kashmir(كشمير)?
It is because of the faults of me and you.
Don't think that the problem of Kashmir(كشمير) is a Kashmiri(كشميرى) problem,
or the problem of the Chechens is a Chechnyan's problem,
or the problem of Falastine(فلسطين) is a Falastini(فلسطينى) problem.
This is a problem of the Muslim Ummah(امة).
Because Allahسُبحانه وتعالى does not know these different states and nations.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى knows one Ummah(امة); one Ummah(امة).
So, whenever there's a punishment or there's a problem or there's a suffering in one part of the Ummah(امة).
It is the suffering for all of us.
And we are all held responsible for it.
So the problems we are going through now are because of us; And we are responsible for solving them.
قَالُوا أُوذِينَا مِن قَبْلِ أَن تَأْتِيَنَا وَمِن بَعْدِ مَا جِئْتَنَا ۚ
They said; We had suffered troubles before you came to us and since you've came to us.
But Musa(موسى) told them;
قَالَ عَسَىٰ رَبُّكُمْ أَن يُهْلِكَ عَدُوَّكُمْ وَيَسْتَخْلِفَكُمْ فِي الْأَرْضِ فَيَنظُرَ كَيْفَ تَعْمَلُونَ۝
It may be that Your Lord will destroy your enemy and make you successors on Earth so that He may see how you act.
Allah will give you a victory over your enemy.
And Allah will give you Khilafah(خِلَافَه). But you have to go through the sacrifice.
That's the natural path to achieve victory.
And then Musa(موسى) told his people in the Ayah(آية) before;
قَالَ مُوسَىٰ لِقَوْمِهِ اسْتَعِينُوا بِاللَّهِ وَاصْبِرُوا ۖ إِنَّ الْأَرْضَ لِلَّهِ يُورِثُهَا مَن يَشَاءُ مِنْ عِبَادِهِ ۖ وَالْعَاقِبَةُ لِلْمُتَّقِينَ۝
He said; Seek help from Allah and be patient.
We have to be patient; Verily, the Earth is Allah's;
He gives it as a heritage to whom He wills of His slave and blessed in the end for Al-Muttaqin(المتقين).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى sent to Musa(موسى) Ayaat(آيات); signs.
How many signs do we already know of up till this moment?
Two;
Which are the stick and the hand.
The Ayaat(آيات) in total were nine.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَلَقَدْ أَخَذْنَا آلَ فِرْعَوْنَ بِالسِّنِينَ وَنَقْصٍ مِّنَ الثَّمَرَاتِ لَعَلَّهُمْ يَذَّكَّرُونَ۝
And indeed We punish the people of Pharoah with years of drought and shortness of fruits that they may remember.
So these are another two, which are; the drought and they don't have any fruits.
So now, we have four and then we have another five mentioned in another Ayah(آية).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is sending them Ayaat(آيات) and Allah says;
Whenever We send them a sign, We send them a following sign which is greater than the one before it.
So, Allah is sending them powerful signs.
Why? For them to remember.
The stick was not enough; The hand was not enough.
So Allah sent on them drought.
Drought; they would get no rain.
And;
نَقْصٍ مِّنَ الثَّمَرَاتِ
They would have less fruits.
Al-Hassan(الحسن) says; these two signs are one.
And he would replace another one with Al-bahr(البحر); he would count the splitting of the sea as one sign.
So then we have five left.
Okay now, when these two signs occurred; Firaun(فرعون) and his people came to Musa(موسى) and they told him;
Can you please ask your Lord to release us from this drought and from this problem?
So they sent him a delegation from the government to meet with Musa(موسى) and tell him; Please! Release us from this problem.
Musa(موسى) made Dua(دُعَا) to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى provided them with rain and fruits again.
فَاِذَا هُمْ يَنكُثُونَ۝
They broke their promise to Musa(موسى).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَأَرْسَلْنَا عَلَيْهِمُ الطُّوفَانَ
The next sign was the flood.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى made the Nile River flood.
So, it would flood on the banks; it would cover their fields and then the water would stick there.
So they cannot plant in the fields.
The water doesn't want go anywhere.
It was an amazing flood; it's a miracle.
The Nile River flooded and the water went over the banks.
And then the water stayed right there; it didn't move.
So, all of the fields were covered; So they cannot plant.
So, they want to Musa(موسى) and they said;
وَلَمَّا وَقَعَ عَلَيْهِمُ ٱلرِّجْزُ قَالُواْ يَٰمُوسَى ٱدْعُ لَنَا رَبَّكَ بِمَا عَهِدَ عِندَكَ ۖ
لَئِن كَشَفْتَ عَنَّا ٱلرِّجْزَ لَنُؤْمِنَنَّ لَكَ وَلَنُرْسِلَنَّ مَعَكَ بَنِىٓ إِسْرَٰٓءِيلَ۝
And when the punishment fell on them, they said;
Oh Musa(موسى)! Invoke your Lord for us; because of His promise to you;
If you will remove the punishment for us; we indeed shall believe in you,
we will believe in you and we are going to let the children of Israel(اسرائيل) go with you.
Musa(موسى) wanted two things; he wanted them to believe and he wanted Firaun(فرعون) to release Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) from the slavery.
Firaun(فرعون) said; I'll give you the two things you want from me;
I'm going to believe and I'm going to release the children of Israel(اسرائيل) with you.
Why was Firaun(فرعون) saying that?
Because he needs Musa(موسى) otherwise his kingdom is going to be lost.
They think in their interest; interest rules.
So they went to Musa(موسى) and they said;
Please; ask Allah; Your Lord, to release us from this punishment.
And if you do so we're gonna believe in you and I'm going to send Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
Musa(موسى) made Dua(دُعَا) to Allah so the water receded.
Now they went to their fields and they started planting again.
They said; We don't know who you are, we're not going to believe and we're not going to send Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى sent on them another sign after At-Tufan(اَلطُّوفَانَ);
وَالْجَرَادَ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى sent on them locusts; grasshoppers; locusts.
Allah sent on them clouds of locusts that would block the sun.
And these clouds would march over their fields and eat anything they find in front of them.
They would eat all of the plants and the trees in the field; they would leave them dead
and then they would march on the houses and eat the wood.
Miracle from Allah; destruction that went over Egypt; clouds of locusts marching over the land of Egypt; destroying everything.
They went to Musa(موسى) begging; Oh Musa(موسى)! asked Allah to release us from this punishment.
We're gonna believe and send Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) with you.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى released that punishment from them;
فَاِذَا هُمْ يَنكُثُونَ۝
They broke their promise again.
Look at this; Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَقَالُوا مَهْمَا تَأْتِنَا بِهِ مِنْ آيَةٍ لِّتَسْحَرَنَا بِهَا فَمَا نَحْنُ لَكَ بِمُؤْمِنِينَ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; they said whatever Ayah(آيَةٍ) you bring us; to work there with your sorcerer; we shall never believe in you.
وَإِن يَرَوْا كُلَّ آيَةٍ لَّا يُؤْمِنُوا بِهَا
Allah says about these people; If they see every sign, they will not believe.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى sent on them another sign which is; Al-Qammal(القمل); Lice or ticks.
Allah sent on them lice and ticks.
These insects that bite your body and they suck the blood.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى sent these insects on them in millions.
Their clothes would be filled inside with lice and ticks.
When they would go in their beds; it would be lined up with lice and ticks.
Wherever they go; these ticks are flying around in their houses and over their bodies.
Their life became terrible and miserable.
They couldn't stand it.
And who can release them from that?
Allah.
They went to Musa(موسى).
Musa(موسى) made Dua(دُعَا).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى took away the punishment.
فَاِذَا هُمْ يَنكُثُونَ۝
They broke their promise again.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله)! Look at the insistence on Kuffr(كفر).
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى sent on them another sign; Frogs.
One of them would put his clothes on; frogs would jump on his body.
He would open up his mouth to eat; a frog would hop in his mouth.
He's eating his food; the frog would land right over it.
He goes to bed; he's crushing frogs under him.
Frogs; wherever they go; It says in the Tafseer(تفسير) that; a group of them would be eating and frogs would jump in their food.
They would open their mouths and their mouths would be filled with frogs.
They went to Musa(موسى); Oh Musa(موسى)! Release us from this punishment; Adhaab(عذاب); Rijs(رجس).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى released them from this;
فَاِذَا هُمْ يَنكُثُونَ۝
They broke their promise another time.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى then sent on them; Ad-Damm(اَلدَّمَ) Blood.
Allah-u-Aalam(اللَّهُ أَعْلمَ), what the exact punishment, was it blood.?
But some of the Mufassireen(مفسرين) say;
that the people of Firaun(فرعون) would go; the people of Egypt would go and take water from the Nile River;
By the time they reach home; it is thick blood.
They will take water out of their wells by the time they want to drink it; it is thick blood.
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); who take water from the Nile River and they would drink it; is water.
They would take water from the wells; it would be water.
With the Egyptians and the people Firaun(فرعون); it would turn into blood.
What can they do? They need to drink.
They went to Musa(موسى) and said; release us from this punishment.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى released them from this punishment but that was the last sign that they would receive.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى gave them enough chances.
And they committed their Kuffr(كفر) with insistence; and they have seen all of the signs; and they were still on the Kuffr(كفر) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says that; Firaun(فرعون) after that; said;
وَنَادَىٰ فِرْعَوْنُ فِي قَوْمِهِ قَالَ يَا قَوْمِ أَلَيْسَ لِي مُلْكُ مِصْرَ وَهَٰذِهِ الْأَنْهَارُ
وَهَٰذِهِ الْأَنْهَارُ تَجْرِي مِن تَحْتِي ۖ أَفَلَا تُبْصِرُونَ۝
أَمْ أَنَا خَيْرٌ مِّنْ هَٰذَا الَّذِي هُوَ مَهِينٌ وَلَا يَكَادُ يُبِينُ۝
Allah says;
And Pharoah proclaimed among his people saying;
Oh my people! Is not mine, the dominion of Egypt and these rivers flowing underneath me; see you not?
Am I not better than this man?
And he can scarcely express himself clearly.
Firaun(فرعون) is saying; Am I not better than this man; who's Maheen(مَهِينٌ); who's degraded; who's weak; He is saying this about Musa(موسى).
وَلَا يَكَادُ يُبِينُ۝
He's not even able to speak.
He's making fun of the speech of Musa(موسى).
Because we said; Musa(موسى) has a problem in speaking.
Firaun(فرعون) was making fun of that.
And then look at the standards of Firaun(فرعون).
Firaun(فرعون) is saying that; he is Maheen(مَهِين); he is degraded; he's low class.
Why?
Firaun(فرعون) says;
Why then are not golden bracelets bestowed on him; or angel sent along with him?
How come Musa(موسى) does not have any gold bracelets?
Look at the standard of thinking of Firaun(فرعون).
How come he doesn't have any gold?
Why is he poor?
Why doesn't he have angels with him?
Why does he need to seek assistance from the weak slaves of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل)?
That is the way they think.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَاسْتَخَفَّ قَوْمَهُ فَأَطَاعُوهُ ۚ
إِنَّهُمْ كَانُوا قَوْمًا فَاسِقِينَ۝
Allahu Akbar(الله اكبر); this Ayah(آية); we need to understand it.
Thus he; Firaun(فرعون); be fooled and misled his people and they obeyed him.
Firaun(فرعون) misled his people and they obeyed him.
Firaun(فرعون) treated them with humiliation and they obeyed him.
Why?
إِنَّهُمْ كَانُوا قَوْمًا فَاسِقِينَ۝
Because they will corrupt people.
Any people who would fall into the trap of following a man like Firaun(فرعون); are corrupt.
Any people who receive the oppression and then they give loyalty to that king or leader are corrupt.
How could you give loyalty to a man like Firaun(فرعون) who was oppressive; Zalim(ظالم)?
That is because of their corruption.
If they were not corrupt; they would not agree to live under the Dominion, under the rule of Firaun(فرعون).
And this Ayah(آية) describes a lot.
When the leaders belittle the people and treat them with humility and the people follow them; That's a sign of their corruption.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَمَآ ءَامَنَ لِمُوسَىٰٓ إِلَّا ذُرِّيَّةٌ مِّن قَوْمِهِۦ عَلَىٰ خَوْفٍۢ مِّن فِرْعَوْنَ وَمَلَإِيْهِمْ أَن يَفْتِنَهُمْ ۚ
But none believed in Musa(موسى) except the offspring of his people;
Zuriyyah(ذرية) means young.
Who are the people who believed in Musa(موسى)?
The young.
There are two Tafseer(تفسير) given of this Ayah(آية)
either it is talking about the young of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل);
meaning that the youth of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) followed Musa(موسى) but the elders didn't.
The other Tafseer(تفسير) is that,
all of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) followed Musa(موسى) and some of the youth of the people of Egypt also follow them.
And these are the ones who follow the Rasool Allah ﷺ, and these are the ones who follow the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء), they are youth.
Because the elders; they're already established.
They have a business; they have a wife; they have children; they have a job.
They're not willing to sacrifice any of that and follow a Nabi(نَبِي).
So they're willing to live, subdued, as long as they will still have the wealth and the family and the kids.
And the ones who are willing to sacrifice and go ahead and give to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى are the youth.
But even though they still had fear; that Firaun(فرعون) would kill them.
This regime was unbelievable.
I mean; people would hear the name of Firaun(فرعون) their knees would shake.
It was a very difficult situation.
وَإِنَّ فِرْعَوْنَ لَعَالٍۢ فِى ٱلْأَرْضِ وَإِنَّهُۥ لَمِنَ ٱلْمُسْرِفِينَ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; Firaun(فرعون) was an arrogant, tyrant on the Earth.
And he was indeed one of Al-Musrifeen(الْمُسْرِفِينَ).
Al-Musrifeen(الْمُسْرِفِينَ) are the once who transgressed the bounds.
He was powerful; a powerful tyrant.
So even these youth who followed him; they still had fear from Firaun(فرعون) that he might kill them.
Syedina Musaعليه السلامwas beginning to feel that, the end with Firaun(فرعون) is soon.
He has given him all of the signs which he received from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; nevertheless, Firaun(فرعون) is still insisting on disbelief.
And things were becoming more difficult on Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَقَالَ مُوسَىٰ يَٰقَوْمِ إِن كُنتُمْ ءَامَنتُم بِٱللَّهِ فَعَلَيْهِ تَوَكَّلُوٓاْ إِن كُنتُم مُّسْلِمِينَ۝
And Moses said; Oh my people! If you have believed in Allah then put your trust in Him; if you are Muslims.
He is preparing them.
Put your trust in Allah; have Tawaqqul(توكل) in Allah.
Because Musa(موسى) knows that this path is a path of difficulty and suffering.
So he's telling his people you need to have Tawaqqul(توكل).
And Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل), they said;
فَقَالُواْ عَلَى ٱللَّهِ تَوَكَّلْنَا رَبَّنَا لَا تَجْعَلْنَا فِتْنَةً لِّلْقَوْمِ ٱلظَّٰلِمِينَ۝
They said; In Allah we put our trust; Our Lord!
What does this mean?
رَبَّنَا لَا تَجْعَلْنَا فِتْنَةً لِّلْقَوْمِ ٱلظَّٰلِمِينَ۝
Oh Allah! Don't make us Fitnah(فِتْنَه) for the non-believers.
The Mufassireen(مفسرين) give a few meanings to that one meaning they say is;
لَا تَجْعَلْنَا فِتْنَةً
Don't give the non-believers; the ability to make for us Fitnah(فِتْنَه) in our religion and drive us out of Islam.
That's one meaning.
So, they're asking Allah to give them; firmness on Sabr(صبر).
So that, they would not lose under the oppression of Az-Zalimeen(الظالمين).
Another meaning is; Don't make us the cause of their disbelief.
Don't make us the cause of their disbelief.
These oppressors or wrongdoers would see that, we are weak and poor and enslaved.
And they would refuse and reject Islam because of that.
So don't make us the cause for the disbelief of the disbelievers.
And then they said;
وَنَجِّنَا بِرَحْمَتِكَ مِنَ الْقَوْمِ الْكَافِرِينَ۝
And save us by our mercy from the disbelieving folks.
Musa(موسى) received Wahi(وحى) from Allah.
Allah is telling him; mark the houses of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
Mark them either with certain code or sign or have a certain flag on them
or it could mean that, we need a map of where the houses of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) are.
Regardless of what it means, the essence of this Ayah(آية) or the understanding that we get from this Ayah(آية) is that
Musa(موسى) and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) they knew the houses of each other.
Whether, it is with a certain mark or a flag or they knew the directions, anyway somehow they knew.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is telling Musa(موسى) tell your people to mark the houses in some way or another.
The Tafseer(تفسير) give different meanings to that but Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَأَوْحَيْنَآ إِلَىٰ مُوسَىٰ وَأَخِيهِ أَن تَبَوَّءَا لِقَوْمِكُمَا بِمِصْرَ بُيُوتًا
Allah says; And we inspired Musa(موسى) and his brother, saying;
Take dwellings for your people in Egypt, this is one order.
The another order, the second order that; Musa(موسى) received in this revelation is;
وَٱجْعَلُواْ بُيُوتَكُمْ قِبْلَةً وَأَقِيمُواْ ٱلصَّلَوٰةَ ۗ
Make your houses, turn your houses into Masajid(مساجد), and establish Salah(صلاة).
Turn your houses into Masajid(مساجد).
What is a Masjid(مسجد)?
The word Masjid(مسجد) is from Sujood(سجود).
Masjid(مسجد) is a place, where you make a lot of Sujood(سجود).
And that's why, our Worship places are called Masajid(مساجد), because we make a lot of Sujood(سجود) in them.
So this means that, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is telling Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) to make their houses centers of worship, centers of Sujood(سجود) to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
وَأَقِيمُواْ ٱلصَّلَوٰةَ ۗ
And established prayer.
Why?
Because difficult moments are lying ahead.
Rasool Allah ﷺ; if he was facing difficulty, what would he do?
He would pray.
Whenever, Rasool Allah ﷺ would be in a difficult situation; he would immediately rush into Salah(صلاة).
So, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is telling Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); You need to prepare yourselves.
And you need to make a lot of Sujood(سجود), and you need to turn your houses into places of Ibadah(عبادة), and you need to establish Salah(صلاة).
وَأَقِيمُواْ ٱلصَّلَوٰةَ ۗ
And then in the end;
وَبَشِّرِ ٱلْمُؤْمِنِينَ۝
And give the believers; the glad tidings; the victory is soon.
Give them the glad tidings.
Musa(موسى) made his Dua(دُعَا) against Firaun(فرعون).
But he did not do it until, he exhausted all means possible.
He used every possible mean.
He was presented with all of our signs; but he disbelieved in them and rejected them.
Musa(موسى) tried everything possible.
Soft words; presenting him with nine Ayah(آية); one after another.
Giving him Targheeb(ترغيب), by giving him Tarheeb(ترهيب), nothing worked with Firaun(فرعون).
In the end, when Musa(موسى) used all possible means, then Musa(موسى) made the Dua(دُعَا) against Firaun(فرعون) and what did he say?
وَقَالَ مُوسَىٰ رَبَّنَا إِنَّكَ آتَيْتَ فِرْعَوْنَ وَمَلَأَهُ زِينَةً وَأَمْوَالًا فِي الْحَيَاةِ الدُّنْيَا رَبَّنَا
رَبَّنَا لِيُضِلُّوا عَن سَبِيلِكَ ۖ
Musa(موسى) said; Oh Allah! You have indeed bestowed on Firaun(فرعون) and his chiefs; splender and wealth in this life of this world.
Musa(موسى) saying; Oh Allah! you have given Firaun(فرعون) a lot. And then, what did he Say?
رَبَّنَا لِيُضِلُّوا عَن سَبِيلِكَ ۖ
Musa(موسى) is saying; They're using this wealth to mislead people from Your path.
This wealth, which is in the hands of Firaun(فرعون) is not used for Your sake, but it is used against Your religion.
رَبَّنَا اطْمِسْ عَلَىٰ أَمْوَالِهِمْ
He said; Oh Allah! Destroy their wealth.
This wealth which they have, which they are using against Islam and against Your religion.
Oh Allah! Destroy it.
اطْمِسْ عَلَىٰ أَمْوَالِهِمْ
وَاشْدُدْ عَلَىٰ قُلُوبِهِمْ
And harden their hearts.
فَلَا يُؤْمِنُوا حَتَّىٰ يَرَوُا الْعَذَابَ الْأَلِيمَ۝
So that, they will not believe until they see the painful torment.
Musa(موسى) is making Dua(دُعَا); Don't guide Firaun(فرعون).
Oh Allah! Do not guide him.
Don't make him believe until, he sees the punishment and it's too late.
It's an interesting Dua(دُعَا). We usually always make Dua(دُعَا); Oh Allah! Guide.
Musa(موسى) over here is making a Dua(دُعَا);
فَلَا يُؤْمِنُوا حَتَّىٰ يَرَوُا الْعَذَابَ الْأَلِيمَ۝
Oh Allah! Don't make him believe until, he sees the painful punishment in front of his eyes, but then it's too late.
This Dua(دُعَا) was not made in the first year or the second year.
This Dua(دُعَا) was made when Musa(موسى) reached to the conclusion that, there is no hope in Firaun(فرعون).
He tried every means possible.
And he's making this Dua(دُعَا); why?
Because he has seen that Firaun(فرعون) and the evil of Firaun(فرعون); it is going to cause the misleading of the believers.
So the Maslaha(مصلحۃ), the interest is, in destroying Firaun(فرعون) and getting rid of him,
because he has become a cause of misguidance for the guided.
So, in the end; Musa(موسى) and that's why, Musa(موسى) and Nuh(نوح) were the two Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) Rasool Allahﷺ said;
Were strong and were harsh on the non believers.
And then, who were the two, which were mild?
Eesa(عيسى) and who?
And Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم).
Eesa(عيسى) and Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) and that's why, in one Hadith(حديث) Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
That you Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), you are similar to Eesa(عيسى) and Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم)
and you, Umar(عمر); You are similar to Musa(موسى) and Nuh(نوح).
Because Nuh(نوح) has also made a Dua(دُعَا); Oh Allah! Destroy the non-believers.
While, we know that; Sayidina Eesa(سيدنا عيسى) and Sayidina Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم); they always were giving another chance.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said;
قَدْ أُجِيبَت دَّعْوَتُكُمَا
Allah said; Your Dua(دُعَا), the Dua(دُعَا) of both of you was accepted.
The Ayah(آية) before; who was making the Dua(دُعَا)?
Musa(موسى).
But in the Ayah(آية), the following it Ayah(آية) says;
قَالَ قَدْ أُجِيبَت دَّعْوَتُكُمَا
Allah said; Verily, the invocation of you both is accepted.
So, why does it say; the two of you?
The Mufassireen(مفسرين) say that, Musa(موسى) was making the Dua(دُعَا) and Haroon(هارون) was saying; Ameen(آمين).
That's the explanation that the Mufassireen(مفسرين) give.
Therefore, the Dua(دُعَا) was actually done by both.
Even though, Musa(موسى) was the one who was saying it, but Haroon(هارون) was saying; Ameen(آمين).
And that's why, when we are in Salah(صلاة); the Imam(اِمَام) is making Dua(دُعَا);
it is all of us who are making Dua(دُعَا) together.
Because when you say; Ameen(آمين) and that's why we say after Al-Fatiha(الفاتحه); Ameen(آمين).
What is the Dua(دُعَا) in Al-Fatiha(الفاتحه) that we're saying Ameen(آمين) for?
اهْدِنَا الصِّرَاطَ الْمُسْتَقِيمَ۝
Guide us to the straight path.
So, all of us say; Ameen(آمين) which means; Oh Allah! Accept.
وَأَوْحَيْنَا إِلَىٰ مُوسَىٰ أَنْ أَسْرِ بِعِبَادِي إِنَّكُم مُّتَّبَعُونَ۝
And we inspired to Musa(موسى) saying; Take away my slaves by night, verily you will be pursued.
Now you understand, why the houses were marked?
Because the order of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) to leave will be sudden.
So Musa(موسى) needs to know, where the homes of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) are located.
So that, they can immediately leave when the order of Allah comes.
Because Firaun(فرعون) was preventing them from leaving.
Firaun(فرعون) has taking them as slaves and servants.
So he does not want to release Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
One of the things that Musa(موسى) has called Firaun(فرعون) to, from the first meeting that he had with him;
أَنْ أَرْسِلْ مَعَنَا بَنِي إِسْرَائِيلَ۝
Send with me; the children of Israel(اسرائيل); Release them.
So when the order of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى was revealed for Musa(موسى); to leave with the children of Israel(اسرائيل).
They have to have a plan, already prepared.
So that, they could leave suddenly, without Firaun(فرعون) knowing.
So the commandment from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى came; in the form of revelation to Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى);
وَأَوْحَيْنَا
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى revealed the order to him;
أَنْ أَسْرِ بِعِبَادِي
Asri Bi'ibadi(أَسْرِ بِعِبَادِي) means; leave at night-time.
So they left at-night time; all of them.
We don't know exactly, how many they were.
But the Mufassireen(مفسرين) they say that;
they were 600,000 fighters, and then add to that the woman and the children and the old.
So this was a huge nation.
And they say, that they have been in Egypt for a little over 400 years.
Because the Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); how did they get into Egypt?
With Yusufعليه السلام and his brothers; Al-Asbaat(الاسباط), his 11 Brothers.
They lived in Egypt and they multiplied; and within 400 years, they were a nation of 600,000.
So this nation left in at night-time.
The news was conveyed to Firaun(فرعون), his spies obviously knew about it.
So they told Firaun(فرعون) about it.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَأَرْسَلَ فِرْعَوْنُ فِى ٱلْمَدَآئِنِ حَٰشِرِينَ۝
Then Pharaoh sent callers to all cities.
إِنَّ هَٰؤُلَاءِ لَشِرْذِمَةٌ قَلِيلُونَ۝
Verily, these indeed are but a small band.
وَإِنَّهُمْ لَنَا لَغَآئِظُونَ۝
And verily, they have done, what has enraged us.
وَإِنَّا لَجَمِيعٌ حَٰذِرُونَ۝
But we are all assembled; amply fore-warned.
Let's look at this Ayaat(آيات);
Firaun(فرعون) is now mobilizing his army to follow Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) left.
Firaun(فرعون) is gathering and collecting his soldiers.
And look at, what Firaun(فرعون) says?
إِنَّ هَٰؤُلَاءِ لَشِرْذِمَةٌ قَلِيلُونَ۝
These are small group that's number one.
He said;
وَإِنَّهُمْ لَنَا لَغَآئِظُونَ۝
And they are enraging us;
وَإِنَّا لَجَمِيعٌ حَٰذِرُونَ۝
But we are all going to be cautious.
Firaun(فرعون); even though, he's saying; they're a small group.
But he's saying that, we're going to prepare for this a lot.
And we're going to gather, all of our army for this purpose.
I find that, a little bit similar to the situation in the world today.
They always say that Islamic fundamentalists are few, it's not a lot of people.
Nevertheless, they're having high profile meetings all over the world to counter their effect.
And you find that the biggest leaders of the world will come together to discuss the children who are throwing rocks in Falastine(فلسطين).
Kids; who are throwing stones in Falastine(فلسطين).
You find the presidents and the kings of the world; coming and discussing; how can we deal with this problem?
شِرْذِمَةٌ
They say; they are small group, kids; children.
Very similar to what Firaun(فرعون) did.
Even though, it's a small group.
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى puts the fear in the hearts of enemies from the believers, even if it’s a small group.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَأَخْرَجْنَاهُمْ مِنْ جَنَّاتٍ وَعُيُونٍ۝
Firaun(فرعون) was gathering all of his army.
Notice; Firaun(فرعون) was gathering; not half of it, not 75%; he was gathering all of his army.
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَأَخْرَجْنَاهُمْ مِنْ جَنَّاتٍ وَعُيُونٍ۝
We expelled them, from gardens and springs.
Allah was expelling them.
Firaun(فرعون) was gathering all of his army to follow Musa(موسى).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى wanted Firaun(فرعون) to gather all of his army so that, they can all be expelled.
وَكُنُوزٍ وَمَقَامٍ كَرِيمٍ۝
Treasures and every kind of honorable place.
كَذَٰلِكَ وَأَوْرَثْنَٰهَا بَنِىٓ إِسْرَٰٓءِيلَ۝
Thus, we cause the children of Israel(اسرائيل) to inherit them.
فَأَتْبَعُوهُم مُّشْرِقِينَ۝
They followed them at sunrise.
Musa(موسى) and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) they left at dark, at night.
Firaun(فرعون) and his army were ready by the morning.
Firaun(فرعون) and his army have better equipment, stronger weapons, more powerful weapons, larger army,
so they were able to catch up.
They were faster than Musa(موسى) and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
Musa(موسى) and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) were traveling East.
Firaun(فرعون) his army were following them.
Musa(موسى) and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل), they reach to the Red Sea.
Actually, they were moving and Firaun(فرعون) is behind them, following them
the group of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل), the ones who are towards the end.
They started seeing in the back, in the horizon, Firaun(فرعون) and his army.
And they kept on trying to move as fast as they can but then suddenly, the Red Sea was in front of them, so they couldn't move.
And now Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) are looking to their back,
and they see that Firaun(فرعون) is coming closer and closer, and they look to the front, and they saw, they find the Red Sea.
What was the reaction of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل)?
فَلَمَّا تَرَٰٓءَا ٱلْجَمْعَانِ قَالَ أَصْحَٰبُ مُوسَىٰٓ إِنَّا لَمُدْرَكُونَ۝
And when the two hosts saw each other, the people of Musa(موسى) said;
We are surely going to be overtaken.
The sea is in front of us, Firaun(فرعون) is behind us, we're dead.
And it is said that, there are mountains on the side, there is no way, we can go.
It is said that Musa(موسى) was towards the end.
So Musa(موسى) and Haroon(هارون) and Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) they made it all the way to the front to the sea and they stood there.
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) are looking at Firaun(فرعون), he's coming closer and closer.
And they're putting pressure on Musa(موسى), What are you doing?
They're going to overtake us, they're gonna kill us, the seas is in front of us, Firaun(فرعون) is towards our back, mountains on the side.
Musa(موسى) does not believe all of this.
He said;
كَلَّا ۖ
No!
إِنَّ مَعِيَ رَبِّي سَيَهْدِينِ۝
Allah will guide me.
He does not believe what he sees, he does not believe what he hears,
but he believes the unseen, which he can neither hear nor see.
The sea is in front of him, the army of Firaun(فرعون) is towards his back, mountains on the side, where can he go?
What can he do?
Musa(موسى) saying;
كَلَّا ۖ
No!
إِنَّ مَعِيَ رَبِّي سَيَهْدِينِ۝
I believe Allah.
I believe in Allah, that He will guide me.
Allah has promised me, I believe in the promise of Allah.
Firaun(فرعون) is closing in
and he's getting closer and closer and they can start seeing the individual soldiers of the army of Firaun(فرعون) right towards their back
and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) are putting pressure on Musa(موسى) and they're telling him; What are you doing?
And imagine the situation of the leadership in that situation.
He's telling them; Allah has promised me that, He will guide us.
And they see Firaun(فرعون) is catching up on them; and he's still telling them; No!
إِنَّ مَعِيَ رَبِّي سَيَهْدِينِ۝
I believe in Allah.
I don't believe, what you're saying and I don't believe that Firaun(فرعون) will be able to overtake us.
Test from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
In that difficult moment, that is when the victory of Allah descends.
When things become very difficult and People start failing, like what happened with Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل)?
They failed in this test.
It is a test for the believers
and the ones who were able to pass it are; Musa(موسى) and Haroon(هارون) and Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون)
and some of the other elders and leaders of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
Then, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى revealed his order;
فَأَوْحَيْنَآ إِلَىٰ مُوسَىٰٓ أَنِ ٱضْرِب بِّعَصَاكَ ٱلْبَحْرَ ۖ فَٱنفَلَقَ فَكَانَ كُلُّ فِرْقٍۢ كَٱلطَّوْدِ ٱلْعَظِيمِ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said; And then, we revealed to Musa(موسى) hit the sea with your stick.
Musa(موسى) hit the sea with the stick.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَكَانَ كُلُّ فِرْقٍۢ كَٱلطَّوْدِ ٱلْعَظِيمِ۝
The sea split up and every portion was like a huge mountain.
Musa(موسى) in front of his eyes, is seeing this water spin up and break into two pieces
and then stand up like two huge mountains in front of his eyes and in front of the eyes of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
They're seeing another Ayah(آية); In front of their eyes.
And then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
Yabasan(يَبَسًا); in another Ayah(آية) in Surat-Taha(سورة طه)
The bottom, the basin of the sea is wet, it's wet, there's water in it and it's mud.
How can they walk on it?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى made it dry.
Not only did it split; did the ocean, sea split, but also the basin became dry.
It is said that, some wind came and took all of the moisture away from it.
So it was firm; Yabasan(يَبَسًا).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; Dry; prepared for Musa(موسى) and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
Musa(موسى) stood and he made all of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) pass through.
And then, he was the last one to go.
When they reached to the other side, Musa(موسى), he hit the sea with his stick; because he wanted to close it.
He hit the sea with his stick.
What divided the sea?
The stick.
But, is it really the stick, that divided the sea?
It is Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, it's not stick.
If you take a stick and hit it with the water; what will happen?
You'll splash water; you will just wet your clothes.
It is not the stick that divided the sea; it is the will of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى that divided the sea.
So why did Musa(موسى) have to use the stick?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will not give you victory until you do your part.
And if the most you could do is; hit the water with your stick, then do it.
The victory of Allah will not come until you do your part.
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى wants Musa(موسى) to do his part.
And we are complaining that, the victory is not here and the reason is; because we're not doing our part.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is gonna perform miracles and is gonna give His victory to the ones who He loves; to the Awliya(اولياء) of Allah,
but they need to do their part.
Rasool Allah ﷺ in the Battle of Badr(بدر).
He put the believers in ranks, he fixed them together, he did everything that is humanly possible and then, what did he do?
He went on a hill and he started making Dua(دُعَا).
He did everything that he can do.
And now, it's time to ask help from Allah.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى sent down 2000 angels to fight with them.
They had to go out, and they had to take all preparations possible, everything humanly possible and then,
when they fulfill that; then they make Tawaqqul(توكل) in Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and Allah will give the victory.
So Allah wants Musa(موسى) to do his part.
The best he can do is; hit the water with a stick.
Now, Musa(موسى) on the other side, thinks that the stick can close it again.
So he is hitting the water with his stick; and he's splashing water but it's not moving.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said;
وَٱتْرُكِ ٱلْبَحْرَ رَهْوًا ۖ
Leave the sea alone.
Allah told Musa(موسى), Leave the sea alone.
وَٱتْرُكِ ٱلْبَحْرَ رَهْوًا ۖ
Why?
Why did Musa(موسى) want to close the sea?
To prevent Firaun(فرعون) from coming.
He's planning, Musa(موسى) is planning.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told him;
وَٱتْرُكِ ٱلْبَحْرَ رَهْوًا ۖ
Leave the sea alone.
Why?
إِنَّهُمْ جُندٌ مُّغْرَقُونَ۝
Because they are going to drown.
After all of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) passed, and Musa(موسى) passed.
Firaun(فرعون) and his army, they went through the basin.
All of them; and when all of the army of Firaun(فرعون); when all of them was on the basin of the sea;
all of them; from Firaun(فرعون) to the last soldier;
then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told the water to return to its natural state of water again.
And it closed on Firaun(فرعون) and his army, because the state of water change for temporary moment.
Water is water.
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى made it change for a while.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى gave it different qualities
and then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told the water to return to its natural state of being water again.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى destroyed Firaun(فرعون) with one of his soldiers, and that's an interesting soldier.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى destroyed Firaun(فرعون) with the source of life.
Water which is the source of life, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى can use it as a soldier.
So, it destroyed Firaun(فرعون).
And it is says in the Tafseer(تفسير) that;
the body of Firaun(فرعون) was spinning up and down in the water, in front of the eyes of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل)
so that, they can see the fate of the enemy of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى the tyrant Firaun(فرعون).
Firaun(فرعون) who said;
أَنَا۠ رَبُّكُمُ ٱلْأَعْلَى۝
I am your highest Lord.
وَمَا عَلِمْتُ لَكُم مِّنْ إِلَٰهٍ غَيْرِي
I don't know that you have any other god, but me, was drowning in front of their eyes.
And now, the fulfillment of the Dua(دُعَا) of Musa(موسى);
When Firaun(فرعون) saw the punishment of Allah, Firaun(فرعون) raised up his finger and he said;
ءَامَنتُ أَنَّهُۥ لَآ إِلَٰهَ إِلَّا ٱلَّذِىٓ ءَامَنَتْ بِهِۦ بَنُوٓاْ إِسْرَٰٓءِيلَ وَأَنَا۠ مِنَ ٱلْمُسْلِمِينَ۝
I believe; that there is no god; but the God of the children of Israel(اسرائيل) and I'm a Muslim.
He believed in Islam.
But he believed when it was too late.
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
تَعرَّفْ إلى اللهِ في الرَّخاء يَعْرِفْك في الشِّدَّةِ
Remember Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in moments of ease, Allah will remember you in moments of difficulty.
Firaun(فرعون) did not remember Allah in moments of ease,
he had wealth, he did not remember Allah,
he had health, he did not remember Allah,
he had life, he did not remember Allah,
he had power, he did not remember Allah,
he had youth, he did not remember Allah.
But now, when he's facing death, when he was seeing the angels of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى descending on him.
He said; I believe.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said;
آلْآنَ وَقَدْ عَصَيْتَ قَبْلُ وَكُنتَ مِنَ الْمُفْسِدِينَ۝
Now, you want to believe when you have committed corruption before;
when you have disbelief before and you have committed corruption.
اَلْيَوْمَ نُنَجِّيكَ بِبَدَنِكَ لِتَكُونَ لِمَنْ خَلْفَكَ آيَةً ۚ
We will save your body and preserver today, so that you could be assigned for the people be after you.
وَإِنَّ كَثِيرًا مِّنَ النَّاسِ عَنْ آيَاتِنَا لَغَافِلُونَ۝
Most of the people are unaware of our signs.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said; Your Tobah(توبة) is not accepted.
When the soul is already coming out and you see the angels in front of your eyes, it's too late.
Jibreel عليه السلام came to Muhammadﷺ and said;
If you have just seen me, when Firaun(فرعون) was drowning, and I was stuffing his mouth with mud.
So that the mercy of Allah would not come on him.
Look at, how much not only Musa(موسى) hated Firaun(فرعون);
even Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل); Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) said that, he was stuffing dirt in the mouth of Firaun(فرعون).
When he saw that, he wants to say;
لَا إلَهَ إلاَّ اللَّه
He started stuffing that dirt in his mouth; so that, the mercy would not come on this man.
You can see that, this man was unbelievable.
He was a tyrant
and for Musa(موسى) to make such a Dua(دُعَا) against him
and to say; Oh Allah! Don't guide him.
And for Jibreel عليه السلام, the angel who would come with Al-Wahi(الوحى) from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء)
Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) is stuffing the dirt in his mouth so that he cannot speak.
That is how bad the tyranny of Firaun(فرعون) was.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى destroyed Firaun(فرعون)
and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
Today we will preserve your body.
Why?
So that you can be assigned for the people after you.
The body of Firaun(فرعون) is being carried from one place to another around the world; mummified.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has saved that body.
And one of the researchers said; they made some research on the body of Firaun(فرعون);
they found a very high concentration of salt in it.
He drowned in salt water.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said that, We preserve the body of Firaun(فرعون);
not to show you the glory of the Firaunic civilization,
not for you to put him in a museum and you go and visit to see the magnificent heritage of Firaun(فرعون),
not to go and take pictures of the body of Firaun(فرعون) to show how great that civilization was.
Firaun(فرعون) who was the worst; whom Allahسُبحانه وتعالى kept his body so that it would be a sign for us.
The people are treating his body and his existence, the exact opposite way of how it was intended.
And that's why Allahسُبحانه وتعالى closes this Ayah(آية) with;
وَلكِنَّ اَكْثَرَ النَّاسِ عَنْ آيَاتِنَا لَغَافِلُونَ۝
But most of the people are unaware of our signs.
People in the world today are unaware of the sign of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Firaun(فرعون) was left behind to be a reminder for us, what will happen to Al-Kafirin(الكافرين).
This is the end result; that is, what will happen to them.
There's something that I want to mention about Musa(موسى) and Firaun(فرعون).
From the people of Firaun(فرعون); very few followed the Da'wah(دعوة) of Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى).
One of them was Momin-Al-Firaun(مومن ال فرعون);
and his story is mentioned in Qur'an and it's a long story.
And his story In sha Allah(ان شاالله) we could talk about it in a separate series about Al-Qass-Al-Qur'an(القص القرآن); The stories of Qur'an.
And then, there's also Asiyah Imra'atu Firaun(آسيه اِمْرَأَتُ فِرْعَوْنَ); who believed.
Asiyah(آسيه); the wife of Firaun(فرعون).
She believed in Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and the message of Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى).
And Asiyah(آسيه) is the one who raised up; Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى); so for him; she was like a second mother.
And Asiyah(آسيه); Allahسُبحانه وتعالى talked about her in Qur'an and Rasool Allah ﷺ also mentioned her in few Ahadith(احاديث).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَضَرَبَ ٱللَّهُ مَثَلًا لِّلَّذِينَ ءَامَنُواْ ٱمْرَأَتَ فِرْعَوْنَ إِذْ قَالَتْ رَبِّ ٱبْنِ لِى عِندَكَ بَيْتًا فِى ٱلْجَنَّةِ
وَنَجِّنِى مِن فِرْعَوْنَ وَعَمَلِهِۦ وَنَجِّنِى مِنَ ٱلْقَوْمِ ٱلظَّٰلِمِينَ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى talks about the wife of Firaun(فرعون).
And she made a Dua(دُعَا) to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
It's an interesting Dua(دُعَا). She said;
قَالَتْ رَبِّ ٱبْنِ لِى عِندَكَ بَيْتًا فِى ٱلْجَنَّة
Oh Allah! Built for me a house in Jannah(جنة).
You might be amazed; why did she specifically asked for house in Jannah(جنة)?
Why specifically a house?
If you would look at her situation, that she would lived in; then you would understand; why she's asking for a house?
She was living in the palace of Firaun(فرعون).
She's the queen.
She has everything, a woman seeking Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) would ask for.
She has everything that Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) can offer.
But the thing that was missing; there was Islam and Eeman(ايمان).
She was living in that place like an alien or a stranger, who doesn't belong there.
She's saying; Oh Allah!
اِبْنِ لِى عِندَكَ بَيْتًا فِى ٱلْجَنَّة
Oh Allah! Built for me a house in Jannah(جنة).
I'm not gonna live in it now, But one day, In Sha Allahu Ta'ala(إنْ شاءالله تعالى), I'll be able to be there.
So, prepare it for me, Build it for me.
And then she said, when she said; Build for me a house in Jannah(جنة), she said;
وَنَجِّنِى مِن فِرْعَوْنَ وَعَمَلِهِۦ
And save me from Firaun(فرعون) and his deeds.
So built for me a house in Jannah(جنة) and then take me out of this environment.
وَنَجِّنِى مِن فِرْعَوْنَ وَعَمَلِهِۦ
Take me out of this place.
She has gold, she has silver, she has the servents, she's the queen over Egypt,
but she's saying; Oh Allah! Take me out of that environment;
take me out; I don't wanna be there.
وَنَجِّنِى مِن فِرْعَوْنَ وَعَمَلِهِۦ وَنَجِّنِى مِنَ ٱلْقَوْمِ ٱلظَّٰلِمِينَ۝
Take me away from these oppressive people.
That is why, Asiyah(آسيه) qualified to be one of the four women, whom Rasool Allah ﷺ praise in Hadith(حديث).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
كَمَلَ مِنَ الرِّجَالِ كَثِيرٌ
The men who were complete were many.
ولم يَكْمُلْ من النساءِ إلااَربَعَة
But the women, who are complete are only four.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; These four were;
Maryam Bint-e-Imran(مريم بنت عمران)
and Asiyah Imra'atu Firaun(آسيه اِمْرَأَتُ فِرْعَوْنَ)
and Khadijah(خديجه) and Fatima(فاطمه).
And we find that these four women are relating in some way or another to Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء).
Two of them raised up Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء)
and one of them was the wife of a Nabi(نَبِي) and the other one was a daughter of a Nabi(نَبِي).
Maryam(مريم) and Asiyah(آسيه) raised up Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء).
Maryam(مريم) raised up Eesa(عيسى) and Asiyah(آسيه) raised up Musa(موسى)
and Khadijah(خديجه) has a wife of a Nabi(نَبِي)
and Fatima Bint-e-Muhammad(فاطمه بنت محمد) is the daughter of the leader of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء); Muhammadﷺ.
These are the only four complete women.
Asiyah(آسيه) believed in the message of Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى), so did Momin-Al-Firaun(مومن ال فرعون),
and then the rest, if we would take the Tafseer(تفسير) of;
فَمَآ ءَامَنَ لِمُوسَىٰٓ إِلَّا ذُرِّيَّةٌ مِّن قَوْمِهِۦ
That would mean some children from the people of Firaun(فرعون)
and there's also Mashitut-Al-Firaun(ماشتت ال فرعون); there's one woman who used to comb for the daughters.
But to sum it up; there are only a few who believe.
This is the end of the story of Musa(موسى) and Firaun(فرعون).
Now, we'll start with a new chapter
and that is The story of Musa(موسى) and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تسلیما کثیرا